------------
Exercise 2.1
------------
1. Run the sequential version on your computer and measure its execution time. From a Linux or MacOS shell
you can time it with time java TestCountPrimes; within Windows Powershell you can probably
use Measure-Command { java TestCountPrimes }; from a Windows Command Prompt you
probably need to use your wristwatch or your cellphone’s timer.
Answer: The time was 6.21 seconds

2. Now run the 10-thread version and measure its execution time; is it faster or slower than the sequential
version?
Answer: 1.6 seconds.

3. Try to remove the synchronization from the increment() method and run the 2-thread version. Does it
still produce the correct result (664,579)?
Answer: No, now two threads can change the value at the same time, creating a race-condition.

4. In this particular use of LongCounter, does it matter in practice whether the get method is synchronized?
Does it matter in theory? Why or why not?

Answer: At first glance it seemed that it should matter because the main thread might see some stale data BUT because of the join the thread that started the other threads sees the changes. From link below: "When a thread terminates and causes a Thread.join in another thread to return, then all the statements executed by the terminated thread have a happens-before relationship with all the statements following the successful join. The effects of the code in the thread are now visible to the thread that performed the join"

https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/essential/concurrency/memconsist.html

------------
Exercise 2.2
------------
1. Write a sequential program to compute the total number of prime factors of the integers in range 0 to
4,999,999. The result should be 18,703,729. How much time does this take?
Answer: 6.4 seconds

2. For use in the next subquestion you will need a MyAtomicInteger class that represents a thread-safe integer.
It must have a method int addAndGet(int amount) that atomically adds amount to the integer
and returns its new value, and a int get() method that returns the current value.
Write such a MyAtomicInteger class.

3. Write a parallel program that uses 10 threads to count the total number of prime factors of the integers
in range 0 to 4,999,999. Divide the work so that the first thread processes the numbers 0–499,999, the
second thread processes the numbers 500,000–999,999, the third thread processes the numbers 1,000,000–
1,499,999, and so on, using your MyAtomicInteger class. Do you still get the correct answer? How much
time does this take?
Answer: Lowest value; 1449ms

4. Could one implement MyAtomicInteger without synchronization, just using a volatile field? Why or why
not?
Answer: No that would not be enough. It would make sure that other threads do not see stale values BUT it does nothing for the possible "read-modify-write" race-condition.

5. Solve the same problem but use the AtomicInteger class from the java.util.concurrent.atomic package instead
of MyAtomicInteger. Is there any noticeable difference in speed or result? Should the AtomicInteger
field be declared final?
Answer: Lowest value was 1283ms, so it is a little bit faster. About declaring it final, there isn't a need to do that in this situation because it is never assigned a new value. BUT declaring the method parameter as final is a goood idea if someone else might is going to be working on the code.

------------
Exercise 2.3
------------
1. In the VolatileCachingFactorizer class, why is it important that the cache ﬁeld is declared volatile? 2. In the OneValueCache class, why is it important that both ﬁelds are declared final?
Answer: This is an example of how to use an immutable object to accomplish thread safety without the use of synchronization. The initial problem was because of the two shared fields "lastNumber" and "lastFactors" which created an "if-then-act" race condition. This could be eliminated by making sure they are only accessed/modified in a single atomic operation. Another way to fix it is to create a new immutable object "OneValueCache" that holds the two values then each time they need to be changed a new instance is created (this fixes the race condition risk). Then the final touch is making the "OneCacheValue" volatile so ensuring that it will always contain the latets values (this fixes the stale data risk).

2. In the OneValueCache class, why is it important that both ﬁelds are declared final?
Answer: How the class is being used, it doesn't really matter BUT doing so ensures that the fields are immutable; its impossible to assign them a new value.

------------
Exercise 2.4
------------
1. Make a thread-safe implementation, class Histogram2, of interface Histogram by adding suitable modiﬁers (final and synchronized) to a copy of the Histogram1 class. Which ﬁelds and methods need which modiﬁers? Why? Does the getSpan method need to be synchronized?
Answer: Making the "increment" method synchronzied gets rid of the "read-modify-write" condition and making the "counts" field volatile makes sure it is always updated correctly. The "getSpan" method does not need to be synchronized since 2 threads do not enter it.

2. Now consider again counting the number of prime factors in a number p, as in Exercise 2.3 and ﬁle TestCountFactors.java. Use the Histogram2 class to write a parallel program that counts how many numbers in the range 0...4 999 999 have 0 prime factors, how many have 1 prime factor, how many have 2 prime factors, and so on;
    Answer:  
    public static void startThreads(int nrOfThreads, int rangePerThread, final AtomicInteger counter, final Histogram histogram) {
        Thread[] threads = new Thread[nrOfThreads];
        for (int threadNr = 0; threadNr < threads.length; threadNr++) {
            final int from = threadNr * rangePerThread;
            final int to = from + rangePerThread;
            threads[threadNr] = new Thread(() -> {
                for (int i = from; i < to; i++) {
                    int nrOfFactors = TestCountFactors.countFactors(i);
                    counter.addAndGet(nrOfFactors);
                    histogram.increment(nrOfFactors);
                }
            });
            threads[threadNr].start();
        }
        for (Thread t : threads) {
            try {
                t.join();
            } catch (InterruptedException e) {
                e.printStackTrace();
            }
        }
    }

3. Deﬁne a thread-safe class Histogram3 that uses an array of java.util.concurrent.atomic.AtomicInteger objects instead of an array of integers to hold the counts. In principle this solution might perform better, because there is no need to lock the entire histogram object when two threads update distinct bins. Only when two threads call increment(7) at the same time do they need to make sure the increments of bin 7 are atomic. Can you now remove synchronized from all methods? Why? Run your prime factor counter and check that the results are correct.
Answer: Yes I can remove synchronized because now the variable for "counts" is an array of AtomicIntegers and that should both take care of the visibility and atomicity issue. And yes, the results are still correct.

4.  Now extend the Histogram interface with a method getBins that returns an array of the bin counts:
	
	public int[] getBins();

Show how you would implement this method for each of the classes Histogram2, Histogram3 and Histogram4 so that they remain thread-safe. Explain for each implementation whether it gives a ﬁxed snapshot or a live view of the bin counts, possibly affected by subsequent increment calls. Note in particular that for instance in the case of Histogram2 it would not be thread-safe to just return a reference to the internal array of integers, since a client who receives that reference could mess with the histogram’s bin counts without any synchronization.
Answer:
- Histogram2:
    
    public int[] getBins() {return counts.clone();}

- Histogram3: 
    
    public int[] getBins() {
        int[] newArray = new int[counts.length];
        for (int i = 0; i < counts.length; i++) {
            newArray[i] = counts[i].get();
        }
        return newArray;
    }

- Histogram4:
    
    public int[] getBins() {
        int[] newArray = new int[counts.length()];
        for (int i = 0; i < counts.length(); i++) {
            newArray[i] = counts.get(i);
        }
        return newArray;
    }

We tested if we got live updates by creating a new thread that printed out the bin array whilst the 10 other threads were working on it and all implementations were not static, they were live and correctly synchronized.

6. In Java 8 there is class java.util.concurrent.atomic.LongAdder that potentially offers even better scalability across multiple threads than AtomicInteger and AtomicLong; see the Java class library documentation. Create a Histogram 5 class that uses an array of LongAdder objects for the bins, and use it to solve the same problem as before.
Answer: Class can be found in solution file.

------------
Exercise 2.5
------------


------------
Exercise 2.6
------------
Consider the class TestStaticCounter as provided as source code. It uses one Long as the counter, synchronizing on it. Its intended behaviour is that it creates two threads, each incrementing count 20 million times in a synchronized way. Accordingly, the expected output would be that whichever thread ﬁnishes last, it produces the same number as the main thread computes. 

1. Describe what you observe when you run the program. 
Answer: Both threads stop prematurely, at least one of them should show "40.000.000" but they show a much lower number.

2. How can you explain what you observe?
Answer: ??

3. Create a version of the program (changing as little as possible) that works as intended.
Answer: Adding a static object as a lock and locking on it fixes the problem nicely, but if we want to take "change as little as possible" literally, we could lock on "Counter.class" that will work to.
